José Malaca

github: tOOnPT

Summary

Mid Web Developer with 4 years of Ruby and Ruby on Rails experience.

I was born and educated in the city that hosts one of the oldest universities in the world, Coimbra (Portugal). Started from the primary school on some small, funny, computer playgrounds and finished the Masters at the University of Coimbra, Informatics Engineering. Today I'm a Software Engineer/Developer always learning, growing, and enjoying work. My focus is all on the backend side of projects, mainly with the Ruby on Rails stack. There are a lot of interesting aspects on this side. APIs, distributed systems, databases, data aggregation, background jobs and so on. There are a lot of challenges that I really enjoy to address to continue develop my skills. Of course, sometimes is required the use of bash scripting and, because most of the times the full stack is called, my JavaScript side exists too. The frontend is very important, I really understand this, so I enjoy to collaborate, learn and contribute as much as I can.

Experience

Ruby/Ruby on Rails Developer, The Loop Co., Coimbra – 2019 – Present

Ruby/Ruby on Rails Developer, IPNlis, Coimbra - 2017 - 2019

- Designed, implemented and tested new features/products for the Lab clients.
- Worked remotely for Portuguese and English companies.
- Main engineer responsible for development of projects, codebases & code reviews.
- Influenced engineering / architectural decisions.
- Influenced product / UX & UI design decisions.
- · Interviewed new software engineers.
- · Mentoring and management of junior developers.
- · Development of automation for build releases and services monitoring.
- Paired with other engineers.
- Pushed for code quality focus.

Ruby/Ruby on Rails Developer, Rupeal, Lisboa - 2015 - 2017

- Designed, implemented and tested new features for the Invoicexpress web application.
- Constantly refactoring to improve the existing codebase.
- From time to time, give a hand to the customer support team. Help to manage client's problems and present/develop solutions.
- Started to build one of the modules that would serve the main application so it could be less monolithic.
- · Paired with other back-end engineers.
- Interviewing and hiring new software engineers.
- · Code reviews across all Invoicexpress web app.

Software Engineer Trainee, BroadScope, Lda, Coimbra - 2003 - 2015

 Worked on my thesis on Data Mining and Natural Language Processing. and on the backend side of a company project about social network analysis.

Education

Universidade de Coimbra (DEI – FCTUC), Portugal - 2014

Master - Informatics Engineering

Skills